Welcome back folks and after encountering or coming across the if else and the logical operators,
the comparison operators, we move on to branching control statements and we do that with a switch
case. Now people coming in from a different programming language, they would have an idea of how
a switch case works. But in Java, we'll just have a look at the syntax. It's mostly like other
C style languages like CC++ or C#, but let's just have a quick look at the switch case
syntax and when we use it. And what were the changes in the recent versions in Java for when it
comes to switch case? So first of all, let's go on and create a new class here again. I'll take control
in and call this a switch case demo, right? So again, we'll just maximize this and I'll just put in
the traditional the customer you may make heard. And now the syntax of writing a switch case is
like this. You say a switch and then just put in a condition and then the braces and then you say
case one, case two, case three, and then a default, right? So now obviously one, two, three,
this is just an example. They do not necessarily need to be ordered. Depends on what you're trying
to compare. They can sometimes be a string. They can sometimes be enumeration as well. Now for the
ones who are wondering what an enumeration is, we have a separate video lined up for what
items are in Java, quite a detailed video about it. But for now, this is the syntax of writing
a switch case. And there were changes made to how the switch case operates in different versions
of Java. I'm going to walk you through some of the most significant changes. And but let's just get
started with using the switch case now, following the syntax. So I'll just take a number from runtime
because as I said, that hard quality values are never recommended. So I'll just say enter a number.
Let's say my requirement is to compare that number with a bunch of values. And this time,
I want to use a switch case. I'll say switch. But first of all, obviously, I need to take this
in a variable. I'll just say in value to new scanner system loaded again. And we'll say dot next
it. Right. And this switch value will just use it in a value. That is a switch case. Sorry.
And then put in multiple cases. And what I'll do is, I'll say if that number, for example, is 10,
right, I want to print that in words, so I'll say 10. And then I'll say a case. Let's say 15. Again,
want to print it in words. I'll say 15. And I'll have one more case. I'll say case three.
And a stout again, I'll just say three. And if none of the matches, I'll say a stout,
no match font. So this works as. So this value is then compared with different case values. First
of all, it would be matched with 10. If it's a match, then whatever you write in the body is executed,
right? And all other cases are ignored, even the default is ignored. Think about default as being
the else to all cases, right? So if 10 doesn't match, then there is a possible match with 15.
If it doesn't match, even three, otherwise the default is executed, right? So let's have a look
at this. And if I hit run, and let's say I enter the number 15, right? So when I hit enter,
what is the output that you're expecting here? So you might wonder that if the value
that obviously I enter the number as 15, this will not be matched, it would move on to the next case,
I'll get 15. And that's it. But you'll be surprised to see I'll get 15, three, and even no match
found. Let's find it out. And that's what you're getting 15, three, and no match found. Now,
what an earth has happened here. I was just expecting 15 to be printed, how on earth were three,
and no match found even printed, that's like an else to all apps. So what happened there is,
there's a condition called fall through that happens in a switch case. So that is, if the value
that you are evaluating in a switch case, it matches any of the case values, then the flu,
the control keeps on falling through. We call it fall through until it finds one of two things,
either the optional break statement or the ending brace of the switch case. So until then,
it keeps on falling through. That's why you would see generally we write after every case,
after every switch rather, we put in a break statement like this.
Now, why do we do that? Because we do not want the fall through to happen. So what happens is,
if any of these case values matches, let's say I enter 10 or 15, right? So I get 15 and then
break, what does break do break immediately gets the control out of the switch case at line number
23. That's it. And in this situation, I wanted that kind of a behavior, but there are situations
where you would want the fall through to happen. And that's why they have kept the break as optional.
But for this kind of a situation, as I told you, the requirement again, it's the program is
programming again is requirement, given the requirement was, and I did not want the fall through to
happen this time. And that's why I put in the optional break statement. I'll just say 15 this time,
it is just 15. So that is how the fall through happens and how you control it with the optional
break statement, right? So, no, then there were some changes with the switch case that happened
in some of the recent versions in the language. I'll just briefly through those changes,
which are quite significant to be true in the next video.